Dorsey William Hyde Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Dorsey William Hyde Papers 1757-1955 (bulk 1905-1955)
MSS26997
Hyde, Dorsey William, 1888-1955
25,000 items
75 containers plus 4 oversize
30.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Librarian and archivist. Correspondence, memoranda, diaries, articles and speeches, genealogical and biographical material, drafts and typescripts, and miscellaneous items relating primarily to the National Archives, where Hyde served as director of archival service (1934-1942).
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Hyde family.; Hyde, Dorsey William, 1888-1955.; Page, Curtis Hidden, 1870-1946. Correspondence and poetry.
Organizations
United States. National Archives and Records Service.
Subjects
American poetry.
Occupations
Archivists.; Librarians.
Provenance
The papers of Dorsey William Hyde, librarian and archivist, were given to the Library of Congress as a bequest in 1955.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Dorsey William Hyde are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Dorsey William Hyde (1888-1955) span the years 1757-1955, with the bulk of the material dating from 1905 to 1955, and contain correspondence, diaries, articles and speeches, genealogical and biographical material, photographs, memoranda, and miscellaneous typed and holograph material. The bulk of the collection relates to the National Archives where Hyde served as director of archival service from 1934 to 1942. Included are papers relating to Hyde’s college years and manuscripts of his unpublished poetry written under the pen name of Edward Ramos. Also included in the collection are correspondence and manuscripts of the unpublished poetry of Curtis Hidden Page.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged by type of material.
Container List
- Diaries and journals, 1909-1935 (Box 1)
- Early family manuscripts, 1757-circa 1900 (Box 2)
- Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Family, 1905-1955 (Box 3-6)
  - General, 1910-1955 (Box 7-19)
- Genealogical and biographical material (Box 20)
- College notes, 1907-1910 (Box 21-23)
- Speeches and writings, 1920-1950 (Box 24-26)
- Notes (Box 27-33)
- National Archives, 1934-1942 (Box 34-63)
- Special Libraries Association (Box 64-65)
- Monday Evening Club (Box 66)
- Invitations, photographs, and poetry (Box 67)
- Miscellany (Box 68-72)
- Curtis H. Page papers (Box 73-75)
- Oversize (Box OV 1-4)
  - Blueprints, diplomas, and charts (Box OV 1)
  - Scrapbooks, circa 1870-1931 (Box OV 2-OV 4)